<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Andrew J. Dyck</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Andrew J. Dyck</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>/project/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/publications/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;As of the end of 2014 (the last time I published), I have published nine peer-reviewed and other publications that have been cited one or more times according to &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.ca/citations?hl=en&amp;amp;user=ce6O2HoAAAAJ&#34;&gt;Google Scholar&lt;/a&gt;. Through publications spanning Economics and Environmental Sciences, these publications have been cited throughout the fisheries and economics domains. As of February 2018, my works were cited nearly 600 times for an  &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H-index&#34;&gt;h-index&lt;/a&gt; measure of 9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More about my publication history can be found via &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.ca/citations?hl=en&amp;amp;user=ce6O2HoAAAAJ&#34;&gt;Google Scholar&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/e/pdy10.html&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt; or  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mendeley.com/profiles/andrew-dyck/&#34;&gt;Mendeley&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;peer-reviewed&#34;&gt;Peer reviewed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sumaila, U. R., Khan, A. S., &lt;strong&gt;Dyck, A. J.&lt;/strong&gt;, Watson, R., Munro, G., Tydemers, P., &amp;amp; Pauly, D. (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;/pubs/Sumaila2010-A_bottom-up_re-estimation_of_global_fisheries_subsidies.pdf&#34;&gt;A bottom-up re-estimation of global fisheries subsidies&lt;/a&gt;. Journal of Bioeconomics, 1–25. &lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10818-010-9091-8&#34;&gt;doi:10.1007/s10818-010-9091-8&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dyck, A. J.&lt;/strong&gt;, &amp;amp; Sumaila, U. R. (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;/pubs/Dyck2010-Economic_impact_of_ocean_fish_populations_in_the_global_fishery.pdf&#34;&gt;Economic impact of ocean fish populations in the global fishery&lt;/a&gt;. Journal of Bioeconomics, 12(3), 227–243. doi:10.1007/s10818-010-9088-3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heymans, S. J. ., Mackinson, S., Little, A., Sumaila, R., &amp;amp; &lt;strong&gt;Dyck, A.&lt;/strong&gt; (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;/pubs/Heymans2010-The_impact_of_subsidies_on_ecological_sustainability_and_future_profits_from_the_North_Sea_fisheries_A_repor.pdf&#34;&gt;The impact of subsidies on ecological sustainability and future profits from North Sea fisheries&lt;/a&gt;. PLoS ONE, 6(5), 13. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0020239&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lam, V. W. Y., Sumaila, U. R., &lt;strong&gt;Dyck, A.&lt;/strong&gt;, Pauly, D., &amp;amp; Watson, R. (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;/pubs/Lam2010-Construction_and_Potential_Applications_of_a_Global_Cost_of_Fishing_Database.pdf&#34;&gt;Construction and first applications of a global cost of fishing database&lt;/a&gt;. ICES Journal of Marine Science, 68, 1–9. doi:10.1093/icesjms/fsr121&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sumaila, U. R., &lt;strong&gt;Dyck, A.&lt;/strong&gt;, &amp;amp; Cheung, W. W. L. (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;/pubs/Sumaila-Fisheries_subsidies_and_potential_catch_loss_in_SIDS_Exclusive_Economic_Zones__Food_security_implications.pdf&#34;&gt;Fisheries subsidies and potential catch loss in SIDS Exclusive Economic Zones: food security implications&lt;/a&gt;. Environment and Development Economics, FirstView, 1–13. doi:10.1017/S1355770X13000156&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sumaila, U. R., Cheung, W., &lt;strong&gt;Dyck, A.&lt;/strong&gt;, Gueye, K., Huang, L., Lam, V., … Zeller, D. (2012). Benefits of Rebuilding Global Marine Fisheries Outweigh Costs. PLoS ONE, 7(7), e40542. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0040542&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sumaila, U. R., &lt;strong&gt;Dyck, A.&lt;/strong&gt;, &amp;amp; Baske, A. (2014). Subsidies to tuna fisheries in the Western Central Pacific Ocean. Marine Policy, 43, 288–294. doi:10.1016/j.marpol.2013.06.012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sumaila, U. R., Cisneros-Montemayor, A. M., &lt;strong&gt;Dyck, A.&lt;/strong&gt;, Huang, L., Cheung, W., Jacquet, J., … Pauly, D. (2012). Impact of the Deepwater Horizon well blowout on the economics of US Gulf fisheries. Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences, 69(3), 499–510. doi:10.1139/f2011-171&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dyck, A.&lt;/strong&gt;, &amp;amp; Ovaska, T. (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;/pubs/Dyck2011-Business_Environment_and_New_Firm_Creation__An_International_Comparison.pdf&#34;&gt;Business Environment and New Firm Creation: An International Comparison&lt;/a&gt;. Journal of Small Business &amp;amp; Entrepreneurship, 24(3), 301–317. doi:10.&lt;sup&gt;1080&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;08276331&lt;/sub&gt;.2011.10593540&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-publications&#34;&gt;Other publications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sumaila, R., &lt;strong&gt;Dyck, A. J.&lt;/strong&gt;, Cisneros-Montemayor, A. M., &amp;amp; Watson, R. (2011). Global Fisheries Economic Analysis. In V. Christensen &amp;amp; J. Maclean (Eds.), Ecosystem Approaches to Fisheries: A Global Perspective (pp. 272–282). Cambridge University Press. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cambridge.org/gb/knowledge/isbn/item5738847/&#34;&gt;http://www.cambridge.org/gb/knowledge/isbn/item5738847/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dyck, A. J.&lt;/strong&gt; (2008). Potential Self-Employment Earnings and Selection Effects in Canada (Master’s paper). Queen’s University, Kingston, ON.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sumaila, U. R., Khan, A. S., &lt;strong&gt;Dyck, A. J.&lt;/strong&gt;, Watson, R., Munro, G., Tyedmers, P., &amp;amp; Pauly, D. (2011). Subsidies to Fisheries in Regional Seas. In V. Christensen, S. Lai, M. Lourdes, D. Palomares, D. Zeller, &amp;amp; D. Pauly (Eds.), The State of Biodiversity and Fisheries in Regional Seas (Vol. 3). Vancouver, BC: Fisheries Centre.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Canadian Football Stats for R</title>
      <link>/project/canadianfootballr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/canadianfootballr/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Data Saskatchewan</title>
      <link>/project/opendatask/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/opendatask/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since 2011, I&amp;rsquo;ve been organizing hackathons and collecting open data sources for the province of Saskatchewan, Canada. I cannot take credit for for it, but since the project began there have been 2 open data portals spring up in Saskatchewan (&lt;a href=&#34;http://open.regina.ca/&#34;&gt;Regina&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;http://opendata-saskatoon.cloudapp.net/&#34;&gt;Saskatoon&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continue to pull together whatever scattered open data sources may exist into the project website, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.opendatask.ca/&#34;&gt;http://www.opendatask.ca/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sask Bike Collision Data Visualization</title>
      <link>/project/sask-bike-collisions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/sask-bike-collisions/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am an individual motivated by data-driven decision making, especially when applied to environmental issues. I have worked as a Fisheries Economist, Credit Risk Analyst, and founded two non-profit organizations, OpenFisheries.org and Open Data Saskatchewan. These two organizations are focused on improving the data availability, accessibility, and promotion of the message of transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife Jen and I have a daughter and two cats. We enjoy travel and spending time outdoors as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compute the product of a column of data using SQL</title>
      <link>/post/2014-01-12-compute-the-product-of-a-column-of-data-using-sql/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-01-12-compute-the-product-of-a-column-of-data-using-sql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In SQL, summing a column of numbers is relatively trivial, and the size of the dataset isn&amp;#8217;t important. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;brush: sql; title: ; notranslate&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;SELECT 
  SUM(X) as SUMOFX
FROM data_table;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathematically, what we are doing here is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$SUMOFX = \sum_{i=1}^n X_i$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if we find ourselves in the unfortunate situation to compute this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$PRODUCTOFX = \prod_{i=1}^n X_i$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, it won&amp;#8217;t be as easy to use the SQL code above, but we can use &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E_(mathematical_constant)&#34;&gt;Euler&amp;#8217;s number&lt;/a&gt; and a property of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_logarithm&#34;&gt;natural logarithm&lt;/a&gt; to also make this task a trivial one. The equation that we are going to exploit is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ln(x*y) = ln(x) + ln(y)$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which gives us a functional relationship between the product and sum of two numbers. This allows us to change our above SQL code to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;brush: sql; title: ; notranslate&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;SELECT
  exp(sum(log(X))) as PRODUCTOFX
FROM data_table;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s probably really rare for this to be useful in any sort of production environment, however, I hope that this trick could save someone the hassle of having to code up a custom solution to compute a product for data that&amp;#8217;s already in a relational database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short script to backup MySQL database from Python</title>
      <link>/post/2010-11-03-short-script-to-backup-mysql-database-from-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2010-11-03-short-script-to-backup-mysql-database-from-python/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mysql.com/&#34;&gt;MySQL&lt;/a&gt; is normally thought of as the relational database management system that many websites are built on, I&amp;#8217;ve found it to be pretty useful for many non-web tasks. Some advantages to using MySQL is that it&amp;#8217;s cross platform so I can use it on my Linux and Windows computers and the availability of the gui tool &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.phpmyadmin.net/&#34;&gt;phpMyAdmin&lt;/a&gt; which is also cross-platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use phpMyAdmin, or you&amp;#8217;re a linux geek, you know that backing up your MySQL database to a .sql file is easy. There is a point-and-click interface for phpMyAdmin and you can use mysqldump in a terminal on linux. Turns out this also works on windows with a small tweak and can be called from a Python script as well if you are using that language for development&amp;#8230;.and if you&amp;#8217;re not you should really consider it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steps to backup a MySQL database running on windows from Python&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;My default install of WAMP2 for Windows 7 didn&amp;#8217;t set an environment variable for the MySQL folder so I added it by adding the text &amp;#8220;;C:\wamp\bin\mysql\MySQL 5.1.36\bin&amp;#8221; without quotes to the windows PATH by right clicking &amp;#8220;My Computer&amp;#8221; &amp;gt; Properties &amp;gt; Advanced settings &amp;gt; Environment variables.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now you should be able to run mysql from the command line from any folder. Try it by opening a command window (win + r &amp;gt; cmd &amp;gt; OK) and typing: &amp;#8220;mysql -u username&amp;#8221;. Pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now you&amp;#8217;re set to run MySQL commands from Python (or PHP, etc. as well I imagine). The following few lines of code will backup an entire database to a temporary directory in your root directory. Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;brush: python; title: ; notranslate&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;import os
target_dir = &#39;C:\\TEMP\\&#39;
os.system(&#34;mysqldump --add-drop-table -c -u username -ppassword database &amp;gt; &#34;+target_dir+&#34;database.bak.sql&#34;)
&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generate monte-carlo simulated data for simultaneous equations</title>
      <link>/post/2010-10-01-generate-monte-carlo-simulated-data-for-simultaneous-equations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2010-10-01-generate-monte-carlo-simulated-data-for-simultaneous-equations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are many sources around the net describing how to use two-stage least squares (2sls) to estimate a system of simultaneous equations. I won&amp;#8217;t get into the nitty-gritty of simultaneous equations here because there is plenty out there on the web. My purpose for this post is to simply show how one can create an arbitrary dataset that one can use to test the assumptions of estimators used for simultaneity problems. Exploring a known data generating process is a great way to learn about how different estimators perform under different circumstances. In my example I will use a system with two dependent variables, Y1 and Y2, and one independent variable, X1. Note that since this system has only one exogenous variable (X1) it is under-identified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The procedure goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write out the equations in your system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-write the system as two equations expressed as functions of exogenous variables only&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generate the variables in your software package of choice. I&amp;#8217;ll be using Stata although this would be equally easy in R and in python you should be able to solve the systems and generate the data in the program and avoid the algebra.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Write out the system of equations:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y1 = a0 + a1*Y2 + a2*X1 + e1&lt;br /&gt;
Y2 = g0 + g1*Y1 + e2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where a0,a1,a2,g0 and g1 are parameters that we specify explicitly while e1 and e2 are error terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can re-write the system of equations like this using simple substitution:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y1 = (a0 + a1*g0 + a1*e2 + a2*x1 + e1)/(1 &amp;#8211; a1*g1)&lt;br /&gt;
Y2 = (g0 + g1*a0 + g1*a2*x1 + g1*e1 + e2)/(1 &amp;#8211; g1*a1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The following code will produce a dataset with simultaneously determined equations. Copy and paste into Stata and hit enter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;brush: perl; title: ; notranslate&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;clear
set obs 1000

* These are the random variables
gen x1 = rnormal(0,1)
gen e1 = rnormal(0,1)
gen e2 = rnormal(0,1)&amp;lt;/code&amp;gt;

* These are the parameters of our equations
* They can be any value you choose
local a0 = 1
local a1 = 2
local a2 = 3
local g0 = 4
local g1 = 5

* This generates our two dependent variables
gen y1 = (`a0&#39; + `a1&#39;*`g0&#39; + `a1&#39;*e2 + `a2&#39;*x1 + e1)/(1-`a1&#39;*`g1&#39;)
gen y2 = (`g0&#39; + `g1&#39;*`a0&#39; + `g1&#39;*`a2&#39;*x1 + `g1&#39;*e1 + e2)/(1-`g1&#39;*`a1&#39;)
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now, since we know the data generating process (DGP) of this dataset, we should use it to test some of the assumptions of the 2SLS estimator. I&amp;#8217;ll explore the 2SLS estimator in an upcoming post but to get you started you can try estimating the parameters using the -ivregress- command below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;brush: perl; title: ; notranslate&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;ivregress 2sls y2 (y1 = x1)
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that the estimated coefficient on Y1 and intercept are 5.003 and 3.984 respectively. These are close to our input parameters so looks like the 2sls procedure works fairly well for this system. Now compare this to the results we&amp;#8217;d find if we just used ordinary least squares (OLS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;brush: perl; title: ; notranslate&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;regress y2 y1
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time we get an estimate for the coefficient on Y1 and intercept of 3.82 and 2.79 respectively. Not good, especially considering that Stata is reporting both of these estimates to be statistically significant.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>