<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sql on Andrew J. Dyck</title>
    <link>/tags/sql/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sql on Andrew J. Dyck</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/tags/sql/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Compute the product of a column of data using SQL</title>
      <link>/post/2014-01-12-compute-the-product-of-a-column-of-data-using-sql/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-01-12-compute-the-product-of-a-column-of-data-using-sql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In SQL, summing a column of numbers is relatively trivial, and the size of the dataset isn&amp;#8217;t important. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;brush: sql; title: ; notranslate&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;SELECT 
  SUM(X) as SUMOFX
FROM data_table;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathematically, what we are doing here is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$SUMOFX = \sum_{i=1}^n X_i$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if we find ourselves in the unfortunate situation to compute this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$PRODUCTOFX = \prod_{i=1}^n X_i$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, it won&amp;#8217;t be as easy to use the SQL code above, but we can use &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E_(mathematical_constant)&#34;&gt;Euler&amp;#8217;s number&lt;/a&gt; and a property of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_logarithm&#34;&gt;natural logarithm&lt;/a&gt; to also make this task a trivial one. The equation that we are going to exploit is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ln(x*y) = ln(x) + ln(y)$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which gives us a functional relationship between the product and sum of two numbers. This allows us to change our above SQL code to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;brush: sql; title: ; notranslate&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;SELECT
  exp(sum(log(X))) as PRODUCTOFX
FROM data_table;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s probably really rare for this to be useful in any sort of production environment, however, I hope that this trick could save someone the hassle of having to code up a custom solution to compute a product for data that&amp;#8217;s already in a relational database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short script to backup MySQL database from Python</title>
      <link>/post/2010-11-03-short-script-to-backup-mysql-database-from-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2010-11-03-short-script-to-backup-mysql-database-from-python/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mysql.com/&#34;&gt;MySQL&lt;/a&gt; is normally thought of as the relational database management system that many websites are built on, I&amp;#8217;ve found it to be pretty useful for many non-web tasks. Some advantages to using MySQL is that it&amp;#8217;s cross platform so I can use it on my Linux and Windows computers and the availability of the gui tool &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.phpmyadmin.net/&#34;&gt;phpMyAdmin&lt;/a&gt; which is also cross-platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use phpMyAdmin, or you&amp;#8217;re a linux geek, you know that backing up your MySQL database to a .sql file is easy. There is a point-and-click interface for phpMyAdmin and you can use mysqldump in a terminal on linux. Turns out this also works on windows with a small tweak and can be called from a Python script as well if you are using that language for development&amp;#8230;.and if you&amp;#8217;re not you should really consider it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steps to backup a MySQL database running on windows from Python&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;My default install of WAMP2 for Windows 7 didn&amp;#8217;t set an environment variable for the MySQL folder so I added it by adding the text &amp;#8220;;C:\wamp\bin\mysql\MySQL 5.1.36\bin&amp;#8221; without quotes to the windows PATH by right clicking &amp;#8220;My Computer&amp;#8221; &amp;gt; Properties &amp;gt; Advanced settings &amp;gt; Environment variables.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now you should be able to run mysql from the command line from any folder. Try it by opening a command window (win + r &amp;gt; cmd &amp;gt; OK) and typing: &amp;#8220;mysql -u username&amp;#8221;. Pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now you&amp;#8217;re set to run MySQL commands from Python (or PHP, etc. as well I imagine). The following few lines of code will backup an entire database to a temporary directory in your root directory. Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;brush: python; title: ; notranslate&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;import os
target_dir = &#39;C:\\TEMP\\&#39;
os.system(&#34;mysqldump --add-drop-table -c -u username -ppassword database &amp;gt; &#34;+target_dir+&#34;database.bak.sql&#34;)
&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>